[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
tonight we're going to see how that
principle of action leads to a principle
of energy and energy
conservation but before we do that I
want to uh I want to
clarify no why quibble not clarify
correct something that I said last time
uh at the end of the hour at the end of
the two hours I tend to get tired and I
make mistakes I made a mistake last time
it was a linguistic mistake more than
anything uh I said something was cholis
I meant centrifugal or I should have
been centrifugal let me go
back uh and just do correctly the motion
of a particle in a plane described by a
radius a distance from the origin and an
angle do it correctly and uh get all the
pieces which I sort of did a little bit
hastily last time again the rules of the
game are begin with the system you're
interested in find the coordinates or or
not find but a combination of find and
invent a set of coordinates to describe
the system write down the kinetic energy
the potential energy that gives you a
lran gives you an action and from the
action you can derive the OA lrange
equations of motion for those
coordinates so for example for the
particle in two
Dimensions moving around on a
plane uh we can describe its location by
two coordinates we could use X and Y of
course or we can use r
r and Theta
distance from the origin and angle from
the horizontal for
example then the components of velocity
now we could choose to describe the
velocity by the X and Y components of
velocity but we can also use the r and
angular components of velocity the
component of velocity along the radial
Direction and the component of the
Velocity perpendicular to it to describe
the um uh the velocity Vector right the
component of a velocity along the radius
Vector that's just let's call it V subr
and that's just r dot the time
derivative of
R the other component which I can call V
Theta let's call it V
Theta it means the component of the
Velocity in the direction perpendicular
to the
radius right that's not Theta Dot but
it's R * Theta
dot why because a given rate of change
of the angle will correspond to a larger
velocity the further are the further
away you are okay a given angular
rotational velocity Theta dot will give
you a larger overall velocity the
further away you are proportional to R
so these then are the components of the
velocity in the two directions R and the
perpendicular
direction if you choose components of
the Velocity along perpendicular axes
then the square of the Velocity is just
the sums of the squares sums of the
squares of the components of velocity
are the magnitude of the Velocity vector
and the kinetic energy is just 1/2 the
mass of the particle time v r 2 + V
Theta 2 so that just becomes r
2+ R 2 Theta do
2 now just to make it more interesting I
also imagined that there was a potential
energy but in particular a potential
energy which only depends on distance
from the origin now that of course is
not a law of thought there you could
imagine potential energies which depend
also on the
angle but it's especially interesting in
many contexts to study stud the central
Force problem the central Force problem
is the one where the force points toward
or away from the origin and is
equivalent to the statement that the
potential energy only depends on R and
not Theta so let's subtract off minus U
of
R that's not the energy now that's the
lran all right let's work out Lan's
equations let me remind you what they
are the oiler lrange equations
uh I'll write them in a general context
first we first construct the Del
derivative of L grangian with respect
to the time derivative of any one of the
coordinates let's this Qi let's pick one
of the coordinates call it
Qi no I'm specializing to the special
case where U only depends on r as I said
there's nothing wholly about that but
for example it is true of gravitational
forces the force of the sun on the earth
uh the potential energy is only only
dependent on the distance from the Sun
it also corresponds to a symmetry
corresponds to rotational symmetry that
the potential energy does not depend on
the angle is simply a statement that the
physics of the problem is invariant
under rotation of axes
okay and we'll come back to
that all right so for each coordinate in
this case the two coordinates are R and
Theta for each coordinate We Begin by
writing down the canonical momentum
conjugate to the coordinate that means
the derivative of the derivative of the
Lan with respect to the velocity or with
respect to the Q dot okay with respect
to the time derivative of the coordinate
and that's called Pi sub I and one says
that Pi sub I is the momentum conjugate
to Q
subi then the oila lrange equations are
that d by DT of this object d by
DT sometimes I'll write just d l by DQ
Dot and sometimes I'll just write Pi sub
I let's write Pi sub
I is equal to the derivative of the
ground
in with respect to Q
subbi we could also write this as d by
DT of the derivative of the lran with
respect to the I generalized velocity Q
subi
dot that's what we got from the
principle of least action when we
applied OA LR method to
it so let's work that out now for the
two coordinates R and Theta first
R all right the derivative of the Lan
with respect to r dot well r dot only
occurs here that's the only place it
occurs and so we can write that Pi
subr which is the same as the derivative
of the time derivative of the derivative
of lunian with respect to r dot that's
just equal to one uh not one half the Mr
Dot
derivative of L with respect to r dot is
just Mr
dot all right so not too surprisingly
the radial component of the momentum is
nothing but the mass times the radial
component of velocity not too
surprising and then our equation of
motion becomes d by DT of this well d by
DT of this that's just mrble dot the
second time derivative of R we assume
the mass is constant so the first term d
by DT of Pi subr is just mrble Dot and
that has to
equal partial of L with respect to
R now there are two contributions to
that R appears in two places one is it
appears in U that's not surprising but
the other is that it appears multiplying
Theta do squared
let's do the theta. squ term first
partial of L with respect to R is
m/2 we're
differentiating M /2 * r^ 2 * Theta do^
2 we're differentiating it with respect
to R all right so that's
m
r Theta do squ do I have that right Mr
theta. s that's one term but then the
other term comes from differentiating U
with respect to R and that's minus du by
Dr
R all right let's erase this
intermediate expression here and just
look now at the equation for R what does
it have well first of all it has
masstimes radial component of a kind of
acceleration here R double
dot uh but then it has first of all over
here the force du by Dr but then it has
this extra
term this extra term depends on the fact
that the particle is
moving in the Theta Direction in other
words it depends on the fact that
there's angular
velocity Mr Theta do 2 proportional to
the square of theta DOT first of all
it's
positive it looks like it's an extra
cont contribution to the force we can
kind of think of it as an extra
contribution to the radial component of
force it enters into the equation on the
right hand side as if there were a
positive force what does a positive
force mean a positive force means one
radially
outward so this Force this it's not a
real Force what's its name I called it
coris last time because I was tired
what's the right name for it ugal this
is the centrifugal
force on the particle
which has the apparent
effect of creating a repulsion away from
the
center we're all familiar with it right
and here's its mathematical uh origin it
comes from differentiating L with
respect to r with r but the piece of it
which multiplies Theta do squ
so we don't have
to the lran method is a Mindless method
it requires zero intelligence you just
follow the steps write down L write down
d l by DQ dot differentiate it with
respect to time and set it equal to DL
by DQ you don't have to think very
deeply what's
that yeah we'll have to do theta too we
we've only done R up till now yes what
you mean
not well by definition by
definition I constantly say this over
and over again but then I slip into the
same pattern I I'm always telling young
physicist and old physicist get rid of
the word real and really and actually
and really and all those words nothing I
didn't mean anything it's on the right
hand side of it's on the right hand side
of the equation there it is what is it
you used to
be what I simply meant is it doesn't
come from the derivative of the
potential energy that's all all right it
is part of what is called the
generalized Force okay uh and I
uh I withdraw the
real okay what's
that
well
yes
yes but uh
nevertheless in some sense it's as real
as anything else let's go on let's not
let's not belabor the uh the issue of
whether it's a real force it occurs on
the right hand side of the equation it
tends to have the effect of keeping the
particle away from the origin and that's
not surprising if a particle is moving
with an angular velocity it uh doesn't
uh want to pass through the origin but
here it is centrifugal force okay let's
write down as Michael said let's write
down now the equation for
Theta all right so let's figure out what
pi sub Theta is pi sub Theta let's do it
over here Pi sub Theta that's the
derivative of the lran with respect to
Theta dot all right notice Theta dot
squared
so we have to differentiate Theta do^ 2
and the result is m/ 2 no the two goes
away because Theta do squar when we
differentiate it gets rid of the two m r
2ar Theta dot differentiate Theta Dot
squar and you get twice Theta dot the
two eats up the two in the uh kinetic
energy that's Pi sub Theta now let's
write down the equation for pi sub Theta
it's D by
DT of Pi sub Theta as D
BYT of m 2 Theta dot the whole
thing that's equal to
what that's equal to the derivative of
the lran with respect to
Theta d l by D Theta Thea well take a
look at that lran do you see Theta in it
anywhere I don't I see r i see r dot I
see Theta dot but I don't see
Theta the consequence or the fact that
Theta doesn't appear in the lran is a
consequence in this case of the
rotational invariance of the problem
that I set up nothing depends on that
angle in particular the potential energy
doesn't depend on angle
therefore d l by D Theta is equal to Z
in other words rotational symmetry of
the problem tells us that the rightand
side is
zero now I could work this out in detail
but why
bother why bother since I know that what
this equation says is that Mr R 2 Theta
dot is a constant let's just use it in
that form it's a constant and that means
is a conservation law what is this
quantity called Mr 2 Theta
dot it's the momentum canonically
conjugate to Theta but of course it's
the angular momentum it's the angular
momentum Mr 2 Theta dot the symbol
that's usually used for angular momentum
is capital
L and so instead of fiddling around with
this equation and doing something
complicated ated with it we can simply
say that m 2 Theta dot is equal to the
angular momentum which is constant now
how big is it that depends on the
starting point that depends on the
initial conditions if you know the
initial condition for example if you
know R and Theta and r dot and Theta dot
initially then you know the angular
momentum Forever After because it
doesn't
change that's not true of Mr dot P subar
it does change because of the force and
because of the centrifugal force but the
angular momentum does not change it's
constant and that's what the what the
equation of motion says so again this is
an example of a symmetry telling us that
there's a conservation law and once we
know it we can treat L as a
constant right a constant which is given
to us by the initial conditions for
example that now means let's come over
to this black to this half of the
Blackboard that allows us to solve for
Theta
Dot and it's equal to the angular
momentum divided by Mr
s well that's interesting now we can
come back to the equation for R let's
come back to the equation for
R now that we know something about Theta
dot let's plug it into the equation for
R and what do we get we get an equation
for R which is m r dble dot is equal now
let me first begin writing minus D
UDR minus
dudr that's of course the familiar piece
and then let's work it out
plus m r and now Theta do squared where
where's Theta dot here it is right here
L
2 divided M2 R
4th I've squared theta dot that gives me
l^2 / m^2 R to the 4th let's cancel out
the unnecessary
symbols M cancels against M sared to
give one power of M in the
denominator and R cancels against R4 to
give three powers of R in the
denominator R cubed
L is a constant once we fixed it we
fixed it and the effect the entire
effect of the centrifugal force is now
to tell us that effectively there's a
force on this particle pushing it away
from the origin that's the plus sign
here proportional to 1 ided by the
distance from the origin cubed also
proportional to the square of the
angular momentum and also the inverse
Mass
okay
so this again of course this is nothing
but the centrifugal
force and notice that once you know the
angular momentum once you fixed it by
knowing the initial motion of the system
then the effect of the rotational or the
angular coordinate is to Simply set up
the centrifugal force which is like 1
divided by the distance cubed it gets
very strong when the distance from the
origin gets small
when when the particle has angular
momentum it does not want to get near
the origin it's pushed away from the
origin with a one over R cubed Force far
away when you're far away this one over
R cubed gets small and it's not so
important
yeah is what is what
is it is true of course there are many
ways to say the same
thing uh it
uh if a particle has some angular
momentum first of all if it has some
angular momentum it means it has some
Theta
dot so that means it's not pointed its
velocity is not pointed right toward the
center if the velocity is not pointed
right toward the
center then what this is telling you is
roughly speaking yach wants to move
along a straight line if it moves along
a straight line it never gets too close
to the origin but it's telling you more
than that it's telling you even a rather
powerful force unless it's strong enough
to overcome this one over R cubed and
one of our R Cub is very very strong at
the origin for example the um the
gravitational force or the Kum force
between charged particles is 1 / r s 1 /
R cubed is much stronger at small
distances than 1 / r r s so this is the
dominant thing at small distances and it
tells you that this particle will not
crash that the Earth will not crash into
the Sun as long as it has some angular
momentum okay
well that's uh that's the idea of
centrifugal
force and the main reason I bring it up
two reasons first of all to give you an
an example of how to use lr's equations
the ESS application of Lanas
equations and to give you an example of
a symmetry and how it acts to create a
conserved
quantity all right now uh just
some it's not really mathematics just
some notation that uh you'll see over
and over
again supposing you have a function of a
lot of variables and the problem is for
example to minimize it sometimes you
let's call the variables let's give them
a generic name Alpha sub I I'm mixing up
I'm using lots of letters of the
alphabet just uh to help you um learn
the Greek
alphabet all right so let's suppose we
have a whole bunch
of uh they not coordinates of any
particle or anything they're just a
bunch of variables and we have some
function which depends on
them the rule for finding the minimum of
the function is is that the derivative
of f with respect to all of the alphas
should be equal to zero sometimes you'll
see that stated as Delta f equals
zero sometimes I'm going to state things
in that form let me tell you what that
means Delta f means it means that if
you're at the minimum of a function
let's say the minimum is over here if
you happen to be at the
minimum then a small change in Alpha
let's move an all a small change in all
of the alphas you move from one point to
another this little displacement is just
Delta Alpha let's call it Delta alpha 1
Delta Alpha 2 Delta Alpha all of them
uh what Delta Alpha equals z says is
that if you move away from the
minimum the function doesn't change to
first order the first order in small
variables right how do we see that well
if we calculate the small change in a
function as we move from a point Alpha
to a point Alpha plus Delta Alpha what
happens to the function the change in
the function is the derivative of f with
respect to Alpha
I time Delta Alpha I summ over over I in
other words as you move from one point
to another you get a contribution from
each one of the partial derivatives
if a if you change the arguments of a
function the function changes to first
order ignoring things of order alpha
squar alpha cubed and so
forth which are which are much smaller
than Delta Alpha ignoring
things of scale Delta Alpha squar Delta
Alpha cubed and so forth the change in
the function to first order is just the
derivative of f with respect to Alpha
times the change in Alpha summed over
all the co all of the uh
variables okay to say that Delta Alpha
sorry that Delta f is equal to
zero for any Delta Alpha no matter which
way you move is the same as saying that
all of these partial derivatives are
equal to zero the only way that this can
be equal to zero for all possible
variations the Delta Alphas are called
the variation of alpha for all possible
variations in other words no matter what
direction in the space you
move to say that you're at a minimum to
say that F doesn't change except to
higher order is the same as saying the F
by the alpha is equal to zero for each
one of the alpha
eyes Okay so these say the same thing
that derivative of f with respect to
Alpha for all Alphas equals zero is the
same thing as saying
that the variation of f is equal to
zero when you change Alpha a little bit
this is short hand for the collection of
these equations over here variation when
it says the variation of f is equal to
zero as an
example we studied the principle of
least
action here's a
trajectory and what we wrote was that
the change that the action is a minimum
with respect to any variation and one
way of writing that is just to say that
the change in the action with respect to
a small change in the
trajectory like a small change in the
trajectory the variation of the action
is equal to zero that's another way of
saying that the action is a minimum with
respect to variations of the trajectory
away from the actual trajectory
that's just a
notational uh a
notational a notational
notation okay now we want to get to the
heart of tonight's lecture which is the
connection between
symmetries and conservation laws we
talked about it a bit up till now I gave
you the examples of uh rotational
symmetry which will do in Greater depth
translational symmetry but there can be
other more complex
symmetries which I won't be very
specific about but will be more
General all right let's uh let's erase
this Blackboard
and the idea of a symmetry is a change
that you can make
in the system that doesn't affect the
action for example if we have some
system of particles moving
around and the particles are interacting
with each other but not interacting with
some external object then if we take the
whole system including its entire motion
and we replace it by a corresponding
system that's been shifted a little bit
shifted over by a small amount small
small or large for that matter then the
action won't change why because the
action doesn't
depend on the location of the individual
objects but only their relative location
that's an assumption of course but more
than an assumption it defines the notion
of symmetry under translation that the
action doesn't change when you translate
the
system another
example is pick an origin
and rotate everything relative to that
origin by the same angle move all the
particles by the same
angle start the system over again the
action for a given trajectory if we
displace the entire trajectory will not
change as a consequence under the
assumption or as a consequence of the
idea that uh the system is invariant
under rotational transformations
okay so basically a symmetry is an
operation that you can do on a system a
change that you can make in the
coordinates that doesn't affect the
action
uh and in particular I'm interested in a
kind of symmetry which is called an
infinitesimal symmetry A Small Change in
a system you can build any change out of
small changes for example if I want to
rotate a system by
180° I can think of it as being built up
by a lot of little Transformations Each
of which is a rotation by a small angle
another possibility is translation where
if I want to say that a system is
invariant under being translated by a
meter I can say it's invariant under an
operation of translating it by a
centimeter but do it 100
times okay so it's sufficient in most
cases to understand the effect of small
Transformations Transformations which
only displace a system a little bit in
other words working to first order in
small
quantities all right so let's let's
define now first of all a transformation
on a
system it's a change in the
coordinates under a transformation
coordinates let's say Q subi change the
Q subi plus something small let Epsilon
be a small number times some
function I of
Q when I say F subi of Q I mean that F
subi can depend on all of the
q's it's a little displacement of the
system if here is your configuration
space q1 Q2 so forth
then wherever you happen to be the
transformation defines a little
displacement to a new location that
displacement in general can depend on
where you are where you
start but it's a
small transformation small in the sense
that Epsilon is a small quantity and
will keep track of things to order
Epsilon all right so it's a displacement
of the system but not necessarily A
displacement along an
axis some more complicated kind of
displacement a rotation would be an
example a rotation in the case of a
rotation if I were to just use X and
Y the change in X will depend on where
you are for example the change in X over
here is different than the change in X
over
here and over here if the system is if
the transformation is a rotation if
we're rotating the system then the
change in x which is positive over here
and negative over here depends on where
you are but a well
defined notion of a small displacement
of a system where the displacement of
each coordinate depends in some specific
way on all of the coordinates so this is
a collection of functions one for each
Direction and what does it mean to say
that we have a symmetry the statement of
symmetry is that if we do such a trans
transformation to the system that the
action of a trajectory doesn't change
all right the action of a trajectory
doesn't change if every coordinate is
displaced in exactly this way that's the
meaning of the term
symmetry what are the consequences of a
symmetry which part of it
all right a symmetry is a
transformation which takes the
coordinates of a system and displaces
them a little bit depending on where you
began right I'll give you I'll give you
some
examples um all right well we're all
right why don't we do an
example let's take the case of a
rotation but not working with angle and
radius but with X and Y
supposing here's the initial location of
a particle X and
Y and now I
rotate about the center here I take
every particle wherever it happens to be
whatever its X and Y are and I rotate it
a little bit that changes every X and
every y but in particular if there's
just one particle let's start with one
particle what is the change in X and
what is the change in y I'm going to
write them down you can check check this
it takes a little bit of trigonometry I
may even work it out later tonight I I
hadn't planned to do it right now but
just as an example the change in
X here's the here's
X now I'm going to rotate the system by
a little angle Epsilon a small angle
Epsilon in this case Epsilon is just a
small angle what happens to X if you
change the angle a little
bit well I'll tell you
it changes by something which depends on
y the change in X is the angle
Epsilon times
y let's see if we can see why that's
true it's easy to see in certain
limiting situations for example if the
starting point is on the x axis over
here what is the change in X when you
change the angle a little bit zero zero
to first order an Epsilon
all right if you change it a little bit
and you're on the axis here x doesn't
change all right that's in agreement
with this formula on the axis means Y is
equal to zero Delta X is equal to minus
Epsilon * y on the other hand supping Y
is up here supposing we start up here
all right then what happens under a
small rotation we get shifted by an
amount proportional to the angle so when
Y is not equal to zero X X changes on
the other hand y doesn't change at this
point Delta y anybody know what Delta Y
is somebody want to guess well no it
depends on where you are I mean if
you're at an arbitrary
Place Epsilon
X for example if you're at this point
over here where X is positive then the
change in y is
positive all right here's an example
where the change in a
coordinate the change in a coordinate
this could be called Delta
Q is proportional to the small number
Epsilon times something which depends on
the coordinates in this case we would
write what would we write we would write
that f subx
f subx is equal to minus y and F suby is
equal to
X that would be an example there are
more complicated Transformations that
you can
imagine uh besides just rotations and
translations we may get to some uh but
not right now but they all have the form
that the coordinates of a system change
by a small amount proportional to some
specific spe ific function a different
one for each one of the
coordinates okay that's the notion of a
transformation a
symmetry is a transformation or a class
of Transformations such as this for
which the action doesn't depend or
doesn't change whenever you do such a
transformation if you like it's a little
displacement of the system or the
coordinates of a system which don't
change the
action let's prove that there's a
conserved quantity whenever there's a
symmetry that's our
goal what
doesn't game
craps dice dice dice craps
yes well it does
indeed in many ways
yep if you didn't put any numbers on a
dice you just made a cube you would say
that a cube has a symmetry but the
Symmetry that the cube has is a discrete
symmetry you can rotate it by
90° along any axis that is not of this
form is not of this form you can't build
up 90° rotations by other 90° rotations
you can build them up on the little
rotations but the Cube doesn't have
invariance on the small rotations a
sphere does a sphere doesn't change when
you rotate it even a little bit and so
you can build up big rotations of the
sphere by lots of little
symmetries whereas the cube has what is
called cubic symmetry which cannot be
built up out of little tiny
infinitesimal Transformations we're
interested in these ones which are built
up out of little
Transformations okay
let's come to the action principle and
see what the action principle tells us
when there's a
symmetry first of all let's begin with a
trajectory connecting a pair of
points vertical axis is
time the horizontal axis is a standin
for all of the coordinates I won't try
to draw them all and the trajectory is a
trajectory of the
coordinates with time
let's first of all suppose that the
trajectory that we start with is a
solution of the equations of motion that
means that the variation of the action
is equal to
zero with respect to all changes of this
trajectory but not quite all changes but
all changes which don't displace the end
points okay now I'm going to make a
change in the trajectory which does
displace the end points what I'm going
to do is I'm going to apply the Symmetry
operation to the trajectory if the
Symmetry operation is translation in
space it's just going to take this
trajectory and translate it in space if
it's rotations it's going to rotate the
trajectory about some uh some axis
whatever it does it moves each point
along the trajectory
by amount Epsilon time F of Q all right
so I'll just draw that by uh by drawing
a little arrow here displacing the
trajectory depending on where
the and so it takes you to some new
trajectory the Symmetry operation takes
you to a new
trajectory and in general the new
trajectory will not pass through the old
end points the old end points will also
get displaced by the Symmetry operation
for example as I said if the Symmetry
operation is just a translate in space
then the end points get translated so
what we're doing is we're making a
little variation of the trajectory but
not an allowable one from the point of
view of the principle of least
action okay what is the change of the
action when we do
this zero why is it zero
not because of the principle of least
action but because I've said this is a
symmetry I've
specified that this is a transformation
which doesn't change the action right
but it is not a trans it is not a
displacement which uh the principle of
least action tells us doesn't change the
action it's the symmetry which tells us
all right let's uh let's calculate the
change in the action
oh we're not doing parallel transport at
the moment later on we'll we'll maybe
even tonight well I doubt it I don't
think we'll get to it tonight but
um wow that was fast tonight it's almost
o' what the lect was half
we're going to get to time translation
symmetry in a little
while time translation symmetry says
you're going to spend the rest of
Eternity sitting here listening to me
forever and
ever is that
a that's
hell all right so what now the variation
of a going from the black trajectory the
red trajectory is zero because it's a
symmetry let's calculate by the standard
method the change in the action the
standard method is what we did when we
worked out the principle of least action
we said first of all the action is the
integral of
ldt that's the action and we said the
change in the action is equal to the
integral the change in the lran when we
change each one of the coordinates Q
subr I time Delta Q sub
I that's this Epsilon well let's just
write let's see which way do I want to
write it I guess we can just write Delta
q
subi but here is Delta Q subi right
here okay and then what else the second
term is the change in the
lran when we change the
velocities time Delta Q subi
dot what did we do next when we did the
principle of least
action we integrated this term by
parts right so as to get rid of the time
derivative over
here what did that do it changed the
sign of this
term put the time derivative on DL by DQ
dot d by DT
and took the time derivative away from
here so that both terms multiply Delta Q
subi in other words we could put a
bracket around
it and bracket off the Delta Q sub
I but this is not necessarily the right
answer because in this case we've also
displace the end points there's an
endpoint contribution coming from the
integration by parts
the endpoint
contribution happens now because Delta Q
subi is not zero at the end points so
we're doing a variation which is not a
legal variation from the point of view
of the least action but nothing to
prevents us from doing it all we have to
do is add back in the extra term does
anybody remember what the extra term
is it's DL by DQ subi
dot time Delta
Q the difference evaluated at the two
end points T1 T2 and T1 in other words
it's the difference of this quantity at
T2 and at T1 it's a difference keep in
mind it's a difference of of of the
quantity at two
points this is the full change in the
action when you displace the trajectory
including a displacement of the end
points
now remember that this first trajectory
that we started with is a solution of
the equations of motion by assumption we
start with a solution of the equations
in other words we start with a
trajectory which does satisfy the
principle of least action or which
satisfies the oil lrange equations what
are the oiler lrange equations the oila
lrange equations are just that this is
equal to
zero the thing inside the bracket here
is just equal to zero by virtue of the
starting trajectory being a solution of
the equations of
motion so that means that this whole
term here can be ignored it's
zero on the other hand because we have a
symmetry and only because we have a
symmetry the variation of the action is
equal to
zero what does that tell us that tells
us that this must be equal to zero on
the one hand let's go through it again
on the one hand the statement that we
have a symmetry tells us that the
variation of a is equal to zero on the
other hand the oila lrange equations for
the initial
trajectory tell us that the thing in
Brackets here is equal to zero the
result is that this term must also be
equal to zero but this term is the
difference between two quantities at two
different
times to say that something
that the difference between a quantity
at two different times is zero is the
same as saying that the quantity is
conserved
okay so we immediately read off from
this a conservation
law if we start with a
symmetry then oh
incidentally
um nobody has asked me about it perhaps
uh I don't need to be asked about it I
have imagined summing over the
coordinates when I write that Delta
a is the derivative of L with respect to
Q subi * Delta Q subi I mean summed over
all
coordinates okay so this quantity over
here is the sum over all the
coordinates DL by DQ subi dot times
Delta
Q that's the conserved quantity
that's the conserved quantity which is
conserved by virtue of the fact that
Delta Q is a
symmetry okay so let's write it down now
the conserved
quantity is D
L by DQ subi
dot
times Epsilon let's put Epsilon out here
times F sub I of Q
well if this is conserved we can get rid
of the Epsilon if the time rate of
change of something is zero it's zero
with or without that constant Epsilon in
front of it so if something is constant
it doesn't change whether it's constant
if you multiply it by Epsilon and so
Epsilon was just a small number that
kept track of the smallness of this term
but what we've
discovered is that as a consequence of
the symmetry
under this particular
displacement a quantity is conserved and
that quantity is DL by DQ dot * F subi
of Q in other words the time derivative
of this is equal to
zero we derived it in a slightly
different form we derived it by saying
it's the same this quantity is the same
at the two end points but if it's the
same for every pair of end points it
means it just doesn't change with time
yes so some over I Su over I I'm going
to leave uh yeah all right Su on
I well that's interesting we've now
found a connection fundamental
connection between symmetries the
principle of least action and uh and
conserved
quantities you'll often hear things like
momentum is conserved because of
translation invariance or angular
momentum is conserved because of angular
rotational
invariance yes that's
true but not every
equation which is translation invariant
has a symmetry that goes along with it
it is necessary or at least sufficient
that the equation is derived from a
principle of least
action we can certainly write down
equations which are translation and
variant but which don't have conser
quantities associated with them they
simply are not derived from a principle
of least
action so it's um the two things
together symmetry plus the assumption
that the equations are derived from a
principle of least action that lead to
the conservation
law right here is the quantity I can
write this another way uh what is DL by
DQ
dot there another
name pi the canonical momentum we can
write this in so many ways but let's
write it in another way this is pi sub
I times if you like just Delta Q
subi Delta Q sub that'll include the
Epsilon we can throw away the Epsilon
out of it it's still conserved so Pi
subi or Pi subi * F subi same thing Pi
subi * F
subi of
Q is conserved
in fact it has a name Pabi qabi is
called the Nera
charge Nera n o e t h e
r Nera was a 19th
century late early 20th century early
20th century 19th or 20th Emily Emily
Emmy Emmy Emmy
nther she died in the
50s well she was she was
late 19th century early 20th century it
must have been the 20th century I'm not
sure when she discovered this theorem
but in any case this is nerus theorem
that there's a conserved charge why is
it called a charge it's called a charge
just by analogy with electric charge
electric charge is conserved and
physicists fall into the habit of
calling anything which is conserved a
charge but
uh uh all it means is a conserved
quantity momentum is a charge energy is
a charge
uh and anything which is conserved is
sometimes referred to as a charge then
it gets complicated because sometimes
we'll speak about the charge not being
conserved and so forth and so on but uh
it's in any case this quantity is called
the nther charge associated with this
particular
symmetry yes yes yes
summation summation over I let's work
out an example or two
the examples that we work out are the
familiar ones that we've done up till
now translation and rotation s just to
see how it works let's suppose we have a
whole bunch of
particles uh
and the whole bunch of particles is
invariant the action L grangian
everything about this particle is in
about the system is invariant if we
translate it of course keep in mind we
have to translate the whole thing if we
translate one part relative to the other
then it's not invariant because there
may be forces between for example if
there are forces between this group and
this group and we move the lower group
then of course we don't have an
invariance it's only moving all of them
that in general defines a
symmetry what is the Symmetry well there
are there are several symmetries there's
one for each direction of space that we
can translate in but let's pick one
let's move along the x axis all right
then each
particle I'm going to write Delta x sub
I I now labels the particles I equals
particle
label if there are 100 particles then I
goes from 1 to 100 it does not label the
directions of space the directions of
space are just X Y and Z so Delta xabi
means that change in the coordinate the
x coordinate of the I particle and
that's just Epsilon they all move
together by an amount
Epsilon all of
them and
furthermore it doesn't depend on where
you are you just translate by amount
Epsilon wherever you happen to be same
amount always the same right what about
for this particular symmetry what about
Delta y
by zero for of course we may also have a
symmetry for moving along the Y AIS but
it would be a different symmetry so for
this symmetry is zero Delta Zu subi also
equal to
zero or another way to say it is that
the fs all of the fs associated with the
X direction are equal to
one
f is equal to one if it corresponds to
the x coordinate of the I particle
they're all equal to one how about for
the Y particle the fs are for the y
direction they're all equal to zero now
let's calculate the nther
charge right the Nera charges we sum
over all of the
particles sum of I of the canonical
momentum conjugate to the x
coordinate time Delta X or times f * F
which is just
one now it's just sum of Pi
subx what is pi subx if the lran is just
the usual lran 12 mv^ 2 plus forces
between the particles and so
forth what is the canonical momentum
conjugate to X for each
particle MX do just the usual momentum
all right so this is just summation of M
subi
xobi
dot that's the ner of
charge uh for translation along the
x-axis just the total momentum the
component along the
x-axis notice we didn't have to know
anything specific about the forces only
that the force doesn't change if you
move the whole
system that no that none of the forces
change or none of the even even weaker
than that the potential energy does not
change if you move all the particles
simultaneously now this of course would
be false if there was another big heavy
object out here exerting forces on all
these particles but if we're talking
about a closed isolated
system and typically a closed isolated
system the energy will not change or the
potential energy will not change if you
move the whole system so we've derived
just from the Assumption of of
invariance under translating the system
we've derived the conservation of
momentum 12 M subi XI
dot of course the same would be true for
the Y component of momentum and the Z
component of
momentum Let's uh work out the
expression for angular momentum
we worked it out in polar coordinates
but now I want to work it out in
cartisian
coordinates X and
Y for Simplicity let's just take a
particle moving again in the Blackboard
X and Y that's
all but let's use X and Y and not R and
Theta all right so we our particle or it
could be a collection of particles
but let's start with one particle it's
coordinati by an X and A
Y those are our two
coordinates
Q are just X and
Y if there are many particles then it's
many x's and y's okay and what is the
transformation we're talking about the
transformation we're talking about is
simply the rotation of the location of
each particle relative to the origin by
an amount proportional to
Epsilon right a while back I wrote down
what the transformation is like what how
what the mathematical rule is for the
rotation I'll write it down again for
you Delta
X is equal to the small angle
Epsilon time Y and Delta
Y is equal to Epsilon * X now you can
work this out using a little bit of
trigonometry if you start with a point
in the XY plane and you rotate the XY
plane everything in the XY plane by a
small angle then you can check that the
components of that particle or that
point change in this manner here it's
just a it's hardly even trigonometry
it's even simpler than that but it's
easy to do uh using a bit of
trigonometry I will simply write down
the
formula Delta X is minus Epsilon * y
Delta Y is Epsilon * X if Epsilon is a
positive number then it corresponds to a
rotation of the system
counterclockwise if Epsilon is negative
it corresponds to a rotation of the
system
clockwise okay
so Epsilon has to be what
yeah Epsilon good Epsilon is measured in
radians thank you yeah not in angle not
in um what are those other units
degrees Yeah right Epsilon and
radians but in fact if it wouldn't
really matter because if I had done it
in radians then there would just be
another um Factor here it would just
change Epsilon would change Epsilon
multiply it by some number okay 60 or
some 57 point something I forget what so
the formula would be the same except
Epsilon instead of being Epsilon would
be some number times
Epsilon okay all right so what then this
this is what we would call
then Epsilon time
FX and this is what we would call
Epsilon time
FY the change in X is Epsilon * FX and
the change in Y is Epsilon * FY we read
off from that that FX is equal to minus
y and FY is equal to
X now let's work out the nther
charge the nther charge where did we
have it here it is right here let's work
it
out it's the sum over the two
coordinates
of pix X that's just the X component of
momentum times FX but FX is minus
y so that's
minus in fact let's just call this
PX standard notation for ordinary linear
momentum momentum along the xaxis minus
PX * y the minus sign comes from this
minus sign over here and the other one
is Plus py *
x py * x - x
py it's Pi * F subi summed over the two
coordinates right X pyus Y
PX that's the angular
momentum it's the thing which is
conserved by virtue of rotation
invariance if there are many particles
then there's a contribution to of this
for each particle summation of all the
particles right again we didn't have to
know very
much about the forces between particles
we didn't have to know very much about
the details all we needed to know is
that the action doesn't change when we
rotate the system about an
axis this is undoubtedly familiar to
many of you this is basically the Z
component of R cross P but we'll come
back to that later uh it's the Z
component of the cross product of the
radius vector and the momentum
vector and there is of course a
component of the angular momentum for
any direction that you might rotate
about this corresponded to rotating
about a direction perpendicular to the
Blackboard if I had some collection of
particles I could have rotated about any
axis and I would have a whole vector's
worth of angular momenta but for our
purposes now the simple thing the
angular momentum of a particle moving in
the Blackboard xpy minus ypx is just a
nther charge associated with the
rotation all right so it's not again
once you know n theorem it's a Mindless
exercise
to uh to calculate the conserved
quantity
of course what is not necessarily
mindless is looking at a system and
figuring out what all its symmetries are
that can sometimes be uh be hard but
once you've located a candidate for a
symmetry you then check does the lran
change when you do that transformation
if not then you go through the Mindless
exercise of calculating the nther charge
and you've and you've discovered a
conserved
quantity so for example exle if you have
the Earth moving around the Sun and you
start the Earth at 11:00 exactly moving
in this Direction with a certain
velocity it'll orbit the Sun and do
whatever it does if you started the
Earth instead of at 11:00 you started it
at
11:01 then it'll Trace exactly the same
path always 1 minute
behind uh the uh the previous trajectory
and we'll find exactly the same
trajectory except displaced In Time by
that one second now what's the
assumption is that nothing in the laws
of physics or in the problem that you're
doing depends explicitly on
time you can imagine situations where
things do depend explicitly on time for
example uh again it usually has to do
with looking at parts of a system but if
our system happened to be pair of pair
of objects and off over here on the
side was a big heavy
Planet which I'm not going to bother
thinking of as part of the dynamical
system but it happens to be moving in
some
way some specified way then the forces
on these objects will be explicitly
dependent on
time they'll be explicitly dependent on
time through the motion of this big
heavy object which we're not taking into
account in our equations of motion we
take it into account simply by saying
the forces are time
dependent that in that
situation if we start these two guys
here at a slightly different time we'll
get a different answer why because the
big heavy Planet here will be in a
different place but if we take a closed
system a closed system not subject to
any kind of
influences which are time
dependent then these kind of systems
typically have a translation and
variance under time
translation in other words change all
the times in the problem by the same
amount by that same 1 second or that
same
Epsilon and a trajectory changed in that
way will stay a solution of the
equations of motion that's called time
translation and variance and we can
well we can draw pictures to illustrate
it and we can write equations to
illustrate what it means and then we can
try to find the consequences of those of
those equations so let's suppose again
that we have
a solution of equations of
motion which we represent by a
trajectory Q's as functions of
time now let's move the
trajectory forward in
time vertical is time and let's move it
forward in time by the amount of Epsilon
that means we take every point in the
trajectory and move it by the same
amount
Epsilon it gets a little tricky over
here because uh well you can see what
happens notice that the end points also
will move because the end points are at
some particular time but let's let's
just move the
trajectory and it'll move to something
that looks like
this
so it's just been pushed up by a mount
Epsilon
all right so T has gone to t plus
Epsilon if you
like what is the transformation on
Q every Q changes notice what happened
let's all right there's two ways to
think about it we can think of this as a
change of the trajectory by moving every
point forward in time but we can also
focus on a particular time if we focus
on a particular time we see that the
trajectory
has moved in this case to the left over
here and to the right over
here so we can think of it in two ways
we can think of it as the trajectory
being moved up or we can also think of
it as the trajectory having been
displaced horizontally but the
horizontal displacement is not fixed it
depends on where you are along the
trajectory okay let's think of it in the
horizontal way what happens to Q at each
instant of time
right Q of T goes to Q of
T minus
Epsilon Epsilon is this fixed amount
that you've shifted the
trajectory why is it minus let's come to
it it's it's actually minus and not plus
uh we'll see why in a
minute so whatever the trajectory was Q
of T plug in TUS Epsilon instead of T
and that's a new trajectory which is
displaced In Time by amount
Epsilon if you doubt that the the sign
here we'll see why it is as I said in a
moment uh what is the change in
Q the change in
Q at the instant
T is equal to the derivative of Q with
respect to T * minus
Epsilon if I displace a function by a
small amount in the
argument then the change in the function
is just the derivative of the function
with respect to T times the change in T
and there's a minus sign here because I
put a minus sign here now you doubt the
minus sign let me show you why the minus
sign is
there supposing for example notice first
of all that what it says is that the
change in Q the little displacement is
proportional to the time derivative of
Q if there was no time derivative that
would mean that the trajectory was
perfectly vertical if the trajectory was
perfectly vertical then there would be
no time derivative dqdt would be equal
to zero and Shifting the trajectory up
and down would not shift it horizontally
at all so the fact that there's a
horizontal shift is because there's a
velocity because the trajectory is
tilted if you like let's suppose the
trajectory is tilted this
way okay and let's move it upward let's
push the trajectory upward in
[Music]
time all right so let's like the
horizontal axis be Q the vertical axis
is time and I've pushed the trajectory
forward in time which way has it moved
in
Q negative so a positive Q dot Q dot is
positive a positive Q dot shifts the
trajectory
backward that's what this minus sign is
doing here a positive Q dot means that
the trajectory shifts backward I always
get confused by this
sign and that's the way I have to think
about it I have to draw a picture and
say if Q dot is positive obviously this
corresponds to Q dot Q increasing is
time increasing then pushing the
trajectory forward in time actually
pushes it back in Q so Delta Q is minus
Q
dot P to P Prime t t t Prime
yeah
yes yeah yeah yeah you could right right
I draw the picture and I see it this way
other people people can see it different
ways all right so that's Delta
Q now let me draw the picture act let me
draw the picture a little more clearly
and then uh and then work out the
consequences of a
symmetry so here's our trajectory let's
say it looks like that our initial
trajectory it's assumed to be a solution
of the equations of
motion now let's push it upward in time
to become this trajectory over
here but let's continue it back a little
bit trajectory could be continued back a
little bit uh so that it matches this
point over here well actually that's not
necessary that's it that's the that's
the
trajectory okay what do we know about
this new red trajectory which has just
been shifted in time we know first of
all that it's still a solution of the
equations of motion
why because we've assumed that we have a
symmetry on the time
translation that's number
one uh what does that tell us that tells
us that the action of the new trajectory
must be the same as the action of the
previous
trajectory that's what it means to have
a symmetry that the action doesn't
change if we shift the trajectory
forward in time like
this let's write that down
oh before we
do let's break up the trajectories into
three
pieces let's see how do I want to do
this yeah all right let's break off a
piece over here since this trajectory
the red trajectory begins at this point
let's chop off this little piece of the
black trajectory we're not going to chop
it off but we're going to wind up
treating it slightly separately from the
rest and since the black trajectory ends
over here let's chop off a piece of the
red trajectory over here as I said we're
not going to chop it off really we're
going to take them into account these
extra pieces but for the moment let's
chop them off and then add back in the
contribution to the action from the
extra little pieces here all
right now
notice what Delta Q is Delta Q is this
displacement over
here let's write down the total change
in the
action from the black trajectory to the
red trajectory the full trajectories the
change in the
action is is equal to zero why because
I've assumed time translation
invariance on the other hand we can also
write it down
explicitly the
integral all right first we'll take the
contribution let's call it from ta a to
TB over
here in other words let's neglect these
little extra terms coming from the end
points here one black extra piece and
one red extra
piece all
right the first contribution comes from
the region between ta and TB and that's
equal to the derivative of the lran with
respect to Q times Delta q but what is
Delta Q that's minus Q Dot
times
Epsilon and what's the second piece the
second piece
is um we can just call this Delta Q the
second piece is
um plus d l by DQ dot time Delta Q
Dot and Delta Q dot we can get by
differentiating this expression over
here it doesn't matter what it is it's
just the usual thing
the difference between the action along
the red piece of the trajectory and the
black piece of the trajectory is just
first of all this expression over here
right then there's the contributions
coming from integrating by
Parts I'm getting tired as you can see I
get tired about this time of night and I
get sloppy okay here's what we have up
till now now we have two extra pieces
the red extra piece over here and the
black extra piece over here let's give
them names A and
B right plus
a minus
B they're just names for the
moment okay what do we do with this what
we do with this is the usual thing we
integrate it by
parts right we integrate it by parts and
that gives us the first term which is
integral DQ the usual thing DL by
DQ minus d by DT of DL by DQ
dot all times Delta Q let's not even
write down what Delta Q is that's the
first
thing ah sorry DT all right the usual
thing good all right now what have I
left out I've left out first of all the
contribution I got by integrating by
Parts all right so that gives me plus Q
dot or sorry plus Delta
Q time DL by DQ
dot
evaluated at
TB minus at
TA okay
but then I've left out these extra
little contributions coming from here
and from
here I'm interested in the difference of
the action on the red trajectory and the
black trajectory that's why I subtracted
A and B the red trajectory has a little
bit of extra over here called a and the
black trajectory has a little bit of
extra over here called B if I'm
interested in the difference between the
action of the two trajectories I want to
subtract a and B all
right so we
have plus
a minus
B and we'll work out in a minute what A
and B are but whatever they are they're
the little pieces coming from the
overhangs because the time intervals
don't begin and end at the same
time what's in here
what's in here is zero why is it zero
because the black trajectory satisfies
the equations of
motion right the black trajectory
satisfies the equations of motion and
this is just the equation of motion in
other words setting this equal to zero
is what tells us that the black
trajectory is equal to a solution of the
equations of motion so this is
zero what is the total change in the
action zero because we have a
symmetry so exactly the same as before
we can neglect
this and we get the contribution from
the end points the difference of a and b
the difference of the end points plus
this extra thing over here that we
didn't see
previously this contribution is exactly
the same as in the Nera theorem that we
studied
before right the contribution coming
from integrating by
Parts because Delta Q is not equal to
zero at the end points over here and
over here Delta Q is not equal to
zero but now we get this extra
contribution over
here what is Delta Q Delta Q is minus
Epsilon * Q dot so we can put a minus
sign here and Epsilon time Q Dot
where did the Q dot come from the Q dot
came from the fact that the variation in
Q is proportional to Q
dot plus a minus B all right now what
are A and
B
uh I don't know whether you recognize
this or not this is a contribution to
the energy but we'll come back to it
leave it the leave it for the moment
what is a and b let's look at a a is
this overhang piece over here the the
red trajectory the red
trajectory continues after the black
trajectory
ends black trajectory ends the red
trajectory goes on for a little bit of
time how much time does the red
trajectory go on
for Epsilon we've shifted the trajectory
ahead by time Epsilon so it goes on for
time
Epsilon what's the extra action on this
little segment of the trajectory over
here well what is the action the action
is the integral of
ldt the lran along here doesn't vary
much between here and here why not this
Epsilon is a very small time interval
imagine Epsilon is an extremely small
time interval now
that means this trajectory doesn't move
very much from here to here if we make
Epsilon really really
small then it goes from here to
here so the coordinates in this extra
little piece here don't change very
much they're practically at a single
point at this point here so that means
we can write down for the lungan just
the lungan at this endend point here
it's just a lran at the end point over
here say at what is that called
TB times the little change in time
Epsilon that's
a again why is it a because the integral
of ldt over this tiny infinite tmal time
difference between t between this point
and this point is time interval Epsilon
over a sufficiently small time interval
an integral is just equal to the
integrand times the time interval so if
Epsilon is small enough this little
extra piece is just a lran at the end
point times Epsilon that's
a what about at the other end at the
other end we have exactly the same
thing
B I don't know why I'm using red and
black I'm getting confused
B is equal to B is L at
TA times
Epsilon
h no ta over
here for some odd reason I've called the
beginning of the trajectory B and put it
a TA and the end of the trajectory a and
put it at
TB
no that's life
so TB or a is the lran at TB at the end
point time Epsilon and B is the lran at
TA time Epsilon where does the Epsilon
come from the Epsilon comes because
we're doing an integral over a small
amount of time lran is just the
integrand again if you do an integral
over a sufficiently small time interval
the answer is just a time interval
Epsilon time the
integrand so those are the two extra end
terms so we can write them down
now we
get yeah yeah we're we're assuming
nothing is singular
absolutely assuming nothing is very
rapidly
varying uh or equivalent correctly that
we can make Epsilon small enough so that
we can ignore the variations of the
function over the interval Epsilon
okay sometimes you can get into trouble
with such assumptions but not
here okay so this is uh this is L at
TB minus L at
TA another
words oh times Epsilon all times Epsilon
everything gets multiplied by
Epsilon and all of that is equal to zero
why zero because we have a symmetry
the change in the action in other words
the change in the
action is simply equal to the term that
we get from the integration by parts
plus this little overhang region
here and this is it that's the
difference in the action of the two
trajectories and it must be equal to
zero everybody understand why it's equal
to zero it's equal to zero by virtue of
the assumption that we have a symmetry
that the action doesn't change when we
move everything ahead a little bit
okay now we can see what goes on
obviously we have a conservation law we
have something evaluated at B what is it
the thing that's evaluated at B is the
lran minus Q dot time DL by DQ
dot evaluated at
B minus the same thing evaluated at
a that difference is equal to zero there
another another way of saying that is
that this quantity is
conserved the
lran minus the sum of I of Qi do DL by
dqi is
conserved this is the kind of term that
we had previously the l byd q dot times
the variation or the small change in Q
now we get this extra term from the from
the overhang
regions so we've discovered a new con
conservation law let's write down what
it's a conservation
of the new conservation law involves the
lran
minus the sum of all the coordinates Q
subi dot DL by DQ subi dot that's Pi
subi that's the thing which is conserved
D because of time translation and
variance mindlessly all we have to do is
calculate the canonical momentum for
each coordinate multiply it by the
corresponding velocity Q
dot put a minus sign in and add the
lran that's n's theorem for time
translation in variance that this is
conserved what is this
called h
minus
H it's conserved and if a thing is
conserved of course so is it's negative
so let's throw a minus sign in this
quantity is conserved and it's called
H the
hamiltonian it's also the
energy it's a conservation law that's
associated with the translation of a
system under time or the Symmetry on the
translation by time and it's called the
hamiltonian and it's the energy of the
system let's work it out for a simple
example to see that it really is the
energy all right so let's work it out
let's
take2 MX do^ 2 minus U of X that's the
lran what's the canonical momentum
conjugate to X it's just MX Dot
that's P or that's
PI what's pi * Q dot that's just Pi * x
dot Pi * x dot the first term here pi x
dot is just equal to MX do 2ar we just
multiply Pi by x
dot so that's the first term here then
we have to subtract the
lran all right so h
then is equal to in this
case h would
be MX do
s that's Pi * x dot minus the grangian
minus the lran the Lan is MX do^ 2 / 2
minus U of
X all right so one term comes from from
the from the pi Q dot that's MX do^ s
and then we subtract off the entire L
grangian notice what happens what's MX
do^ 2us MX do^ 2/ 2 it's just MX do s
over
two notice we're subtracting minus U of
X that means plus U of x
so
indeed this quantity which is conserved
by virtue of the time translation and
variance really is the sum of kinetic
energy and potential
energy this is true very
generally if you like even better it's
the definition of energy in mechanics
the definition of energy is the quantity
which is conserved as a consequence of
uh of um
of time translation and
variance let's see is it worth perhaps
we can
do well let me take some questions at
this point here because this was a this
is a pretty slick derivation but uh you
may have missed some of the Little Steps
so let me go back or let me feeli some
questions at this
point
yeah oh well let's let's let's hold hold
back on angular momentum for a minute I
want to concentrate on this uh
derivation
here
uh just to go back over it
schematically we said that if we if we
translate the trajectory in time a
little bit the action should not change
so that tells us that Delta a is equal
to zero all right then instead of
thinking of translating the trajectory
forward in time we thought of it as a
shift by amount Q
dot well then we calculated the
difference of action along the black
trajectory and the red trajectory
subtracting off these overhang regions
forgetting the overhang regions for a
minute that gave us something which was
proportional to the extra terms that we
get from the integration by parts why
because the end points of the trajectory
move a little bit
we get nothing from the term that's
proportional to the equations of motion
in other words nothing uh that would be
there if the equation of motion is
satisfied on the black trajectory so we
get one contribution coming
from the integration by parts end term
and another contribution coming from
these overhang regions here one of the
contributions is this q. Pi that's the
contribution coming from the integration
by
parts endpoint contribution and then the
other term coming from the end from the
uh from the overhang here is the
difference of L grangian at the two ends
those two terms combined give us the
conservation of the thing that I've
called h
yeah that was for the case that was not
for the case where we're displacing time
it's the case where we are simply
Shifting the
coordinates LED yeah the extra L got
added in because of the shift of time
and these overhang regions that was
only
yeah right when what we did was shift
the trajectory keeping the time in
points fixed that didn't occur so that's
the extra new thing this this thing is
not new that is just equal to Delta Q *
pi that's the same as in the nther
example the extra term comes from here
and it's because of the shift of the end
points and time here okay so it's a
rather neat
fact as long as your system is time
translation and variant and assuming it
comes from a principle of least action
there is always a conserved energy and
this is in classical physics the most
general definition of energy it's the
reason why in all the systems that
you've ever studied there's always
something called Energy that's
conserved but ultimately it does trace
back to the principle of least action
and the time translation and
variance okay so any other questions
about this particular point before I
take questions about other
things yeah
no good good good good good good good
all right so the defin the lights go out
the definition of lran is the integrand
in the
action okay that's the most general
definition and uh as long as the action
exists as long as the L grangian exists
this is the definition of energy if the
energy happens to be a the form of a
conventional kinetic energy or if the
lran happens to be of the conventional
form of a kinetic energy minus a
potential energy then the hamiltonian
will be the kinetic energy plus the
potential
energy okay so this is more General and
more
fundamental for the specific example
where the lran is a sum of terms of this
type a sum of many many terms all the
particles in the world all the different
directions of space they can move in
under those circumstances the
hamiltonian will just be your familiar
kinetic plus potential
energy so as far as definitions go from
this point of view the more fundamental
quantity is lran and the only real
assumption is that it depends on the q's
and the Q
dots right
pull it out of the air he pulls it out
of
experiments right now of course that's
not really in practice what's done and
practice What's Done may be a dirtier
more complicated
procedure and uh but thus far all known
systems including field Theory including
gravitation all these things general
theory of relativity special theory of
relativity they're all of this form
yeah absolutely there many yeah there
are conditions first of all it should be
a function only of the q's and the Q
dots that's one thing and the second
thing which we'll eventually come to
which is
important is uh which we haven't stated
at the moment when we calculate these
pies they're typically functions of Q
and Q dot the pi a partial LEL with
respect to Q dot it's important that you
can solve for the Q dots in terms of the
pies but I don't want to get into that
now yes there are
conditions uh which are
important and uh Define the admissible
uh lunians absolutely this basically
single valued of the connection between
velocities and canonical
momenta but uh we'll come to that when
we uh
yeah to which
this
one this
case I'm not understanding let's
see oh you mean if the trajectory is
going oh do you want me to change the
trajectory or change
all right we can change Epsilon if we
change the sign of Epsilon then we're
moving the trajectory
down
oh you want to change the
trajectory yeah all right then you
change the trajectory it goes this way
you want to change the trajectory so it
goes that way yeah then Q do is negative
if we're moving the trajectory forward
in Time same uh Epsilon is positive then
Q do is
negative okay Q dot is negative minus Q
dot is positive and Delta Q is positive
so that says that Delta Q now is
positive
well first of all we'll do some more
examples the harmonic oscillator in
particular it's lran
formulation
uh but what I want to work into now is
the hamiltonian form of
mechanics the hamiltonian form of
mechanics is Central to the connection
with quantum mechanics now at this point
um we're sort of caught up where I want
it to be we'll get into the ham tonian
form but I think we should also do some
more examples some more practical
examples of the utility of this uh and
uh how you actually work out problems a
couple of problems but is there anything
you would like to cover at this
point yeah
well of course that's not really the way
that it happened of course what the way
that it really happened is the equations
of motion were deduced by from
experiment and then they were cast into
L grangian form by uh people who were
interested in putting equations into L
grangian
form uh
the historical evolution of uh physics
tended to be through equations of motion
for example
uh Maxwell's equations have an action
formulation which I hope to get to uh or
the motion of a Charged particle in a
magnetic field as an action formulation
it's an action formulation which you
probably would not have guessed very
quickly the first thing that was
discovered by Lorent at the end of the
19th century was the equation of motion
the fals ma type equation for a particle
moving in a in a magnetic field and then
later that was put into it was realized
that that had the form of a lunian
equations of motion uh but
ultimately the you don't pull it from
out of your head you either pull it from
the equations of motion which you try to
put in lran form or from uh or from
experiment I'm not sure what the
question was
well okay these days in the days of
quantum field Theory the thing that you
actually measure in experiments is more
closely related to the lran than to the
equations of
motion but uh for example particle
collisions are direct the cross-sections
for particle collisions the events which
happen the individual events the
emission of photons and that sort of
thing is directly connected with terms
in the lran directly and so you read
them off particle physics uh Collision
amplitudes or particle collision uh
probabilities uh that's not classical
physics although the same Lans govern
the classical
limit um In classical physics as I said
the things which were discovered first
were the equations of
motion what was the history of Maxwell's
equations well the history of Maxwell's
equations when went back to uh um
Faraday and Faraday's intuitive insights
into fields and so forth and Maxwell
fiddled with them until they became
consistent and then discovered the wave
equation for light all that stuff later
on uh in the beginning early 20th
century people realized that those
equations had the form of OA lrange
equations for a principle of least
action uh and that the action was a lot
simpler than the uh than the equations
of motion themselves typically
incidentally uh the action is much
simpler than the equations of motion the
simplest
example um let's take the particle
moving in two Dimensions it has this
complicated uh centrifugal form over
here that would not be so easy to guess
on General grounds
the uh the equation is fairly
complicated with the Mr Theta do squ you
wouldn't easily guess these equations of
motion on the other hand 1 12 mv^ 2 plus
the potential energy is very easy to
remember you write it down and then you
do the oila lrange trick on it and you
get the equations of motion so from a
practical point of view it is always
easier to calculate the lran first and
then deduce from it the equations of
motion than it is to calculate the
equation emotion
directly uh I will eventually show you
some fairly difficult examples which are
very easy to think about when you think
about an action next week though not
now well in mechanics as opposed to fuel
Theory it was Hamilton in the you know
little later second half of the 19
century um 186 I'm not sure exactly what
year uh
so this is late uh late 19th century
lrange was earlier first lrange in the
first half of the 19th century then
Hamilton in the second half and of
course the whole thing reached its um
real fruition with quantum mechanics
quantum mechanics makes very very heavy
use of the uh of the hamiltonian form of
mechanics really is the explanation of H
for all of
this okay if there are one or two more
questions I'm reaching the end of my
uh it can be oh yeah
um okay let's come back to it at the
beginning of next time but what happens
if the hamiltonian or lran excuse me is
an explicit function of time
uh then the energy is not conserved why
is that well if the action is an
explicit function of time that means
that the variation of the action when
you push a trajectory forward will not
be zero a trajectory pushed forward in
time will not be a solution of the
equations of motion
anymore uh if the action explicitly
depends on time in other words forces
change with time and so forth then the
new trajectory will not have the same
action as the original
trajectory if that's the case this whole
derivation breaks down and uh the energy
is not conserved but we'll work out next
time remind me the next time I'll work
out what happens to the energy if the L
grangian has an explicit time dependence
in it the answer is energy is not
conserved
[Music]
the proceeding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu